Register of the Vitaliĭ Leonidovich Kataev papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Arms Control File, 1975-1999 (Boxes 5-11)
  - Strategic Arms Reduction Talks (START), 1982-1992
    - Joint declaration of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics and the United States of America relating to future negotiations on START and strategic stability, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Text of the unilateral declaration of the Soviet Union regarding START, undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - Options for START alignment after reduction, undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Possible solutions to the remaining questions of START on the advisory board with S. P. Bartholomew, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - Principals of detour inadmissibility for the future armament reduction agreement (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Miscellaneous documents regarding strategic weapons and strategic command control, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - Texts of the unilateral declaration of the United States of America and the Soviet Union regarding strategic offensive weapons treaty (Box-folder 5: 9)
      Includes extract from the declaration of the Soviet government on December 6, 1986 (regarding non-compliance with the treaty).
    - Progress report to Mikhail Gorbachev, "On Preparedness of the Agreement on Strategic Offensive Weapons,", 1990 May (Box-folder 5: 10)
      Prepared by L. Zaikov, V. Kriuchkov, E. Shevardnadze, A. Iakovlev, D. Iazov, O. Baklanov, and I. Belousov.
    - Suggestions for questions on the strategic offensive weapons agreement for the meeting of the ministers of foreign affairs of the Soviet Union and the United States of America (September 26, 1990, New York), 1990 September 20 (Box-folder 5: 11)
      Includes declaration of the Soviet Union regarding the medium-range bomber Tu-22M.
    - Proposals for the second round of negotiations on strategic offensive weapons and strategic stability, 1990-1992
      - General (Box-folder 5: 12)
        Relates to further process of the reduction of armaments and possible targets of the next stage of the reduction of strategic offensive weapons.
      - Documents prepared at request of the Commission of the Politburo of the CPSU Central Committee regarding an agreement between the USSR and the USA on 50% reduction of strategic offensive weapons, 1990 April (Box-folder 5: 13)
      - Suggestions on the further reduction of strategic offensive weapons of the USSR and the USA (Box-folder 5: 14)
        Includes two working versions of the document.
      - Structure of the strategic forces of the Soviet Union, chart (Box-folder 5: 15)
        Includes comments on the chart.
      - Material on the question of frame agreement of the presidents of the USSR and USA regarding further substantial reduction of strategic offensive weapons, 1992 June 17 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - Additional list of unsolved questions in the agreement on strategic offensive weapons suggested for the discussion in Washington, 1990 September 22-23 (Box-folder 5: 17)
    - Assessment of different agreements on weapons reduction, circa 1991 (Box-folder 5: 18)
    - Additional material for settlement of the main unsolved questions in negotiations on strategic offensive weapons, 1991 February 21 (Box-folder 5: 19)
    - Statement from the Soviet Union "Strategic Offensive Weapons,", 1991 June 7 (Box-folder 5: 20)
      Includes data and technical characteristics.
    - Statement of the President of the Russian Federation regarding strategic forces, 1992 January 29 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - Strategic nuclear-arms-control negotiations, 1986-1998
    - General
      - Facts on the Soviet position in negotiations on nuclear and space armaments including Mikhail Gorbachev suggestions for Reykjavik meeting, 1986 (Box-folder 5: 22)
      - Facts on the main nuclear armaments of Great Britain, France, and China as of 1987 January 1 (Box-folder 5: 23)
      - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "On Our Further Tactical Line Relating to Negotiations with the United Sates on the Questions of Nuclear and Space Armaments,", 1987 February 26 (Box-folder 5: 24)
      - Inquiry of the CPSU Central Committee, "On Additional Directions to the Soviet Delegation in Negotiations on Nuclear and Space Armaments,", 1987 October 27 (Box-folder 5: 25)
      - Inquiry of the CPSU Central Committee, "Directives to the Delegation of the Soviet Union in the Soviet-American Negotiations on Nuclear and Space Armaments in Geneva (The Beginning of the Next Round Is 1988 January 14),", 1988 January 13 (Box-folder 5: 26)
      - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "Directives to the Soviet Delegation in the Tenth Round of Negotiations with the United States on Nuclear and Space Armaments (The Beginning is July 12, 1988, Geneva),", 1988 June 23 (Box-folder 5: 27)
      - Radiation leak from the sunken Soviet nuclear submarine, 1989 December 7 (Box-folder 5: 28)
      - Strategic nuclear weapons issues, material from the Department of International Affairs, CPSU Central Committee, 1990s (Box-folder 5: 29)
      - Express-analysis of the initiatives of the presidents of the Soviet Union and the United States of America in reduction of nuclear armaments and measures of cooperation, Moscow, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 30)
      - Facts on a possible structure of the US and Soviet heavy bombers for 50% reduction of the strategic offensive weapons as of 1998 January 1 (Box-folder 5: 31)
    - Tables of strategic nuclear weapons, 1989-1998
      - General (Box-folder 5: 32)
        Includes tables and charts.
      - Data on correlation of Soviet and American armed forces (Box-folder 5: 33)
      - Fighting strength of the military and navy forces of the USSR and USA (Box-folder 5: 34)
      - Information on Soviet and American submarine-launched cruise missiles, anti-ship missiles, and their ratio (Box-folder 5: 35)
      - Options for the structure of Soviet heavy bombers, intercontinental ballistic missiles, and strategic nuclear forces due to 50% reduction of strategic offensive weapons (Box-folder 5: 36)
      - Options for the structure of American strategic offensive forces due to 50% reduction (Box-folder 5: 37)
      - Tactical atomic weaponry (vehicles carrying nuclear weapons) (Box-folder 5: 38)
      - Statistics of the numerical strength of strategic and intermediate-range nuclear armaments
        - Soviet Union and the United States (Box-folder 5: 39)
        - France and Great Britain (Box-folder 5: 40)
        - China (Box-folder 5: 41)
      - Tactical nuclear weapons material, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 5: 42)
      - Note regarding tactical nuclear weapons from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union to the Embassies of Great Britain, Finland, Denmark, Sweden, Norway, Poland, Federal Republic of Germany, United States of America, and France, 1990 (Box-folder 5: 43)
      - Numerical strength of strategic offensive weapons as of 1990 (Box-folder 5: 44)
      - Structure and numerical strength of the strategic offensive weapons of the USSR and USA, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 5: 45)
      - Facts on numerical strength of strategic carriers and atomic warheads of the USSR, USA, Warsaw Treaty Organization, and NATO, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 5: 46)
      - Data on the ratio and numerical strength of tactical atomic weaponry between the Warsaw Treaty Organization and NATO as of January 1, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 47)
      - Fighting and numerical strength of the strategic offensive armaments of the USSR and USA after 50% reduction as of January 1, 1998 (Box-folder 5: 48)
    - "Houston package" - Houston talks on arms control, 1989-1991
      - About the "Houston package," Kataev's copy, undated (Box-folder 6: 1)
      - Questions related to the "Huston package,", undated (Box-folder 6: 2)
      - Estimation of the stocked nuclear munitions of the United States of America, Great Britain, France, and China (chart) (Box-folder 6: 3)
      - Inquiries on various prospects of development of strategic weapons (Box-folder 6: 4)
      - Directives and resolution from the CPSU Central Committee and suggestions from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the USSR to the Soviet delegation for Soviet-American negotiations on nuclear and space armaments, 1989 May (Box-folder 6: 5)
      - Order from the Council of Ministers of the Soviet Union regarding the visit to American laboratories working on the problems of space armaments by a group of Soviet specialists, 1989 November (Box-folder 6: 6)
      - Information-report from the inter-department working group on ALCM (Air-Launched Cruise Missile), 1990 March (Box-folder 6: 7)
      - Agreement between the Soviet Union and the United States of America about annual exchange of information regarding development of strategic offensive weapons, 1990 August 8 (Box-folder 6: 8)
      - Suggestions of the Soviet Union for a package agreement among States of the Protocol of liquidation, 1990 September (Box-folder 6: 9)
      - Suggestions of the United States of America on the control of production of mobile intercontinental ballistic missiles, 1990 September (Box-folder 6: 10)
        Includes statement about the policy of the Soviet Union regarding TU-22M bombers.
      - Holograph notes from meetings, written by Kataev, 1990 December 7 - 1991 December 2 (Box-folder 6: 11)
      - Analytical information on ALCM (Air-Launched Cruise Missile), 1990 (Box-folder 6: 12)
        Includes memorandum of understanding.
      - Analytical information on SLCM (Submarine-Launched Cruise Missiles), 1990 (Box-folder 6: 13)
      - Soviet suggestions based on the results of negotiations in Reykjavik, 1990 (Box-folder 6: 14)
        Includes list of the major unsolved questions and background material, 1990-1991.
      - Strategic offensive weapons, existing (Box-folder 6: 15)
        Includes technical characteristic of intercontinental ballistic missiles, 1990.
      - Positions (7 articles) of the Soviet Union passed on to the American side, 1991 January 1 (Box-folder 6: 16)
      - Directives for the meeting of the Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union, A. Bessmertnykh, with James A. Baker, 1991 February (Box-folder 6: 17)
      - Progress report in preparation of the draft agreement on strategic defensive weapons, 1991 February 15 (Box-folder 6: 18)
        Includes unofficial document from the American side.
      - Material for meeting of the delegations, Geneva, 1991 February 19 (Box-folder 6: 19)
      - Talking points, Kataev's copy, 1991 April 19 (Box-folder 6: 20)
        Includes Kataev's handwritten notes.
      - Attachment to the sanctioned directives of the fifteenth round of negotiations on nuclear space armaments (beginning April 19, 1991), signed by M. Moiseev and V. Karpov, 1991 April 17 (Box-folder 6: 21)
      - Summary of the agreement on reduction and restraining of the strategic offensive armaments signed on July 31 1991 by the presidents of the Soviet Union and the United States of America and questions regarding ratification of the agreemen, prepared by A. Arbatov (Box-folder 6: 22)
      - Additional material for settlement of the main unsolved questions in negotiations on strategic offensive weapons (on specification of the "Houston package"), undated (Box-folder 6: 23)
  - Nuclear and space missile talks, 1986-1991
    - Ballistic missile defense, space weapons
      - General information on strategic defense initiative (SDI, US), holograph (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - Historic map of the Soviet space missile testing ground (Box-folder 7: 2)
        Belonged to I. Serbin, head of the Department of Defense Industry of the CPSU Central Committee.
      - Principal approach on reduction establishment for launching of experimental anti-satellite equipment in outer space (Box-folder 7: 3)
        Components of the system, satellite basing interceptor missiles. Chart.
      - Material on the questions of nuclear-space armaments for meeting with Ronald Reagan, undated (Box-folder 7: 4)
        Includes the attachment, "Thoughts on Outcome of Major Unsolved Questions of the START (Strategic Arms Reduction Talks) between the Soviet Union and the United States of America." Includes additional thoughts on military-political questions.
      - On the question of the participation of Great Britain in the SDI program (Box-folder 7: 5)
      - Material of the Institute of the United States and Canada regarding development of the position (of the Soviet Union) in negotiations on nuclear space armaments (Box-folder 7: 6)
      - Draft of the agreement between the Soviet Union and the United States of America, "About the Measures of Enhancing Confidence and Ensuring Predictability in the Relations of Their Activity in the Area of Interceptor Missiles" (Box-folder 7: 7)
      - Material from the Defense Department (Soviet Union), "About Interconnection between Reduction of Strategic Offensive Weapons and Compliance with a Space-based Defense (USA) Treaty" (Box-folder 7: 8)
      - Study (of the Soviet counterpart) on launching of ballistic missiles in stratified atmosphere or in space (Box-folder 7: 9)
      - Proposals of the Soviet Union on space issues in negotiations of nuclear space weaponry in Geneva (Box-folder 7: 10)
      - Declaration on the press briefing in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union (first version) (Box-folder 7: 11)
      - Position of the Soviet Union on the question of further negotiations on space and nuclear space weaponry (Box-folder 7: 12)
      - Directives to the representative of the Soviet Union on the Standing Soviet-American Consultative Commission on the thirty seventh session (Box-folder 7: 13)
      - Seminar on the question of regime enhancement of a nuclear space weaponry treaty, forum "For Nuclear-Free World, for Survival of Mankind" (Box-folder 7: 14)
      - Information, "The Real Situation regarding US Claims of Compliance with the Soviet Union with Commitment in the Area of Reduction of Armaments" (Box-folder 7: 15)
      - Strategic Defense Initiative (SDI) expenses in the budget of the United States, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 7: 16)
      - Information on the European Defense Initiative, 1986 April (Box-folder 7: 17)
      - Inquiry on the position of the Soviet Union and the United States in negotiation on nuclear and space armaments, round five, 1986 May 8-June 20 (Box-folder 7: 18)
      - Material regarding Krasnoiarsk anti-ballistic missile (ABM) radar, 1986-1990
        - Map of the object (ABM radar) (Box-folder 7: 19)
        - Official letter from Ronald Reagan to Mikhail Gorbachev regarding Krasnoiarsk ABM radar, 1986 August 12 (Box-folder 7: 20)
        - Thesis for discussion with American counterpart on the questions of transformation of the Krasnoiarsk ABM radar into a center of international cooperation in peaceful space activity (Box-folder 7: 21)
        - Considerations on possible resolution of some questions regarding compliance with the ABM defense treaty (Box-folder 7: 22)
        - Additional argument for Soviet-American meeting to review the ABM defense treaty (Box-folder 7: 23)
        - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "On Liquidation of the Krasnoiarsk Anti-ballistic Missile Radar (ABM Radar),", 1990 March 20 (Box-folder 7: 24)
      - Excerpt from the protocol (minutes of meeting, number sixty six) of the Politburo of the CPSU Central Committee, 1987 May 19 (Box-folder 7: 25)
        Includes proposals from the Ministry of Defense of the Soviet Union at the request of the Politburo of the CPSU Central Committee (October 14, 1986) on questions of specification of the structure of the nuclear forces of the Soviet Union and counteraction to the American program of creation of multi-mission systems in interceptor missiles.
      - Information presented in speech of the Deputy Director of the CIA of the United States, Robert Gates, 1986 November 25 (Box-folder 7: 26)
      - Information for the discussion on the question of "Flat Twin" anti-ballistic missile radar (ABM radar). (Box-folder 7: 27)
        Includes material regarding inspection by American representatives of the Homel (Belorussia) and Moscow areas, 1987 December 20-22.
      - Material related to the International Nuclear Forces (INF) Treaty, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 7: 28-29)
      - Suggestions from the CPSU Central Committee of the Soviet Union regarding American accusations of so-called "violation" by the Soviet Union of the ABM treaty (Box-folder 7: 30)
        Includes resolution of the CPSU Central Committee on this issue, 1987 November 21.
      - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "About the Draft of the Agreement on Reduction and Restraining of Strategic Offensive Armaments and Additional Directions to the Soviet Delegation on Negotiations with the USA Related to this Issue" (Box-folder 7: 31)
        Includes draft resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "Additional Directions to the Soviet Delegation in Negotiations on Nuclear and Space Armaments," 1988 February.
      - Resolution on the American document regarding the structure of the ABM system, 1988 April 9 (Box-folder 7: 32)
        Includes "Defense Acquisition Board (DAB) Approved Architecture Responsive to JCS (Joint Chiefs of Staff) Requirements."
      - Directives to the representative of the Soviet Union on the Standing Soviet-American Consultative Commission for the thirty-sixth session, 1988 November 26 (Box-folder 7: 33)
      - Declaration of the Soviet government regarding the ABM treaty, 1988 October 22 (Box-folder 7: 34)
      - Research analysis of the American SDI program (1983-1989) (Box-folder 7: 35)
      - Directives from the CPSU Central Committee, "About Interconnection between the Upcoming Agreement on Strategic Offensive Weapons and the Acting ABM Treaty,", 1989 June 7 (Box-folder 7: 36)
        Includes resolution of the CPSU Central Committee regarding this issue.
      - Letter to the CPSU Central Committee signed by L. Zaikov, V. Kriuchkov, E. Shevardnadze, A. Iakovlev, D. Iazov, O. Baklanov, I. Belousov, and S. Akhromeev, "On Possible Solutions in Negotiations on Nuclear and Space Armaments,", 1989 November 20 (Box-folder 7: 37)
      - Material on Soviet-American negotiations on nuclear and space armaments (Box-folder 7: 38)
        Includes list of main unsolved questions, thirteenth round, circa 1990 January.
      - Request from the Politburo of the CPSU Central Committee about choosing a location for the construction in the eastern part of the Soviet Union of a new warning perimeter for anti-ballistic missile radar (ABM radar), 1990 April (Box-folder 7: 39)
      - Information on positions of the Soviet Union and the United States of America in relation to the intercontinental ballistic ground-based missiles (ICBM), 1990 April 13 (Box-folder 7: 40)
      - Notes from meeting with Mr. G. Tillman, First Secretary of the American Embassy in Moscow and notes from meeting with Ambassador Jack Matlock regarding arrangements concerning the visits to the ABM radars at Tula and Pechora, 1990 April 2 and 19 (Box-folder 7: 41)
        Includes response from the Soviet side.
      - Material for meeting with R. Bert on the question of the launching containers of the intercontinental ballistic missiles, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1991 February 25 (Box-folder 7: 42)
      - Protocol regarding payload (throw-weight) of the intercontinental ballistic missiles (IBM) and Trident submarine-launched ballistic missiles (Trident SLBM) in connection with the agreement between the Soviet Union and the United States of America on reduction and restraining of strategic offensive armaments, 1991 March 4 (Box-folder 7: 43)
      - Additional material in connection with the next round of negotiations on nuclear space armaments, 1991 April 15 (Box-folder 7: 44)
      - Material on the questions of ABM and space, 1991 June-September (Box-folder 7: 45)
    - Intermediate- and long-range nuclear forces (INF) talks, 1987-1990
      For related material, see CORRESPONDENCE AND REPORTS OF MIKHAIL GORBACHEV, Strategic nuclear-arms-control negotiations/Tables of strategic nuclear weapons, and Strategic nuclear-arms-control negotiations/"Houston package."
      - Inquiry on the effect of the ALCM on START negotiations, undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
        Includes documents on the effectiveness of strategic weapons, mainly rockets.
      - Draft letter of response to James A. Baker regarding ALCM, undated (Box-folder 8: 2)
      - Evaluation of the situation regarding heavy bombers and ALCM, undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
      - Suggestions for consideration of the Defense Council board regarding air-launched long-range cruise missiles, 1987 July (Box-folder 8: 4)
      - Map of the Soviet Union depicting the location of intermediate and long-range missiles as of June 1, 1988 (Map case)
  - Comprehensive test ban talks, 1986-1990
    - Information on the state of the situation of Soviet-American negotiations on reduction and restraining of nuclear tests, undated (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - Draft of the message from the Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union to James A. Baker, undated (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "On Stationing of Seismic Stations near the Nuclear Testing Grounds in the USSR and the USA,", 1986 July 9 (Box-folder 8: 8)
      Includes memorandum of understanding pertaining to the agreement between the Academy of Science of the Soviet Union and the National Resources Defense Council of the United States, 1986 July 5.
    - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee on resumption of nuclear testing, 1987 January 31 (Box-folder 8: 9)
      Includes draft of the press release from the telegraphic agency of the Soviet Union (TASS) on conducting of the underground nuclear explosion in Semipalatinsk (Kazakhstan), 1987 February.
    - Proposal to the CPSU Central Committee, "About the Order of Releasing Information on Conducting an Underground Nuclear Explosion, 1987 May 6 (Box-folder 8: 10)
      Signed by L. Zaikov.
    - Information for the thirty-first session of the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) and directions to the Soviet delegation, 1987 September (Box-folder 8: 11)
    - Suggestions on the control of group explosions for the discussion of the interdepartmental working group, for consideration to V. Kataev from V. N. Mikhailov (Box-folder 8: 12)
      Includes illustrations, 1988-1990.
    - Information on "Cortex" method (hydrodynamic method in estimation of the energy of underground nuclear explosion), 1988 March 16 (Box-folder 8: 13)
      Includes illustrations.
    - Draft of the agreement between the USSR and the USA of the joint experiment on control, 1988 April (Box-folder 8: 14)
    - Material on underground nuclear testing, 1989 May (Box-folder 8: 15)
      Includes charts on conducting underground nuclear tests in the USSR and the USA, 1986-1990.
    - Information on a possible Soviet position on the problem of nuclear tests for the meeting of the ministers of foreign affairs of the USSR and the USA, 1990 March 1 (Box-folder 8: 16)
    - Resolution of the Council of Ministers of the Soviet Union regarding the agreement between the government of the USSR and Swiss Federal Council on cooperation in using nuclear energy for peaceful purposes, 1990 April 7 (Box-folder 8: 17)
      Includes draft of the agreement.
    - Suggestions for the position of the Soviet Union during the next round of Soviet-American negotiations in Geneva on reduction and restraining of nuclear tests, 1990 August 21 (Box-folder 8: 18)
  - Conventional Forces in Europe (CFE) talks, 1987-1991
    - Material on CFE negotiations
      - Undated (Box-folder 8: 19)
      - 1987-1989 (Box-folder 8: 20)
      - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 8: 21-22)
    - Data on correlation of tactical nuclear armaments between the Warsaw Treaty Organizations and NATO (Box-folder 8: 23)